<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>Alex Richey</title>
    <link>https://alexrichey.com</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <description>Software engineer based in NYC. I write about politics and code.</description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2017 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting Up Server Side Rendering with React, Redux, and Django</title>
      <link>https://alexrichey.com/articles/setting-up-server-side-rendering-with-react-redux-and-django.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2017 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <description>My article on server side rendering originally published on Meural's Product Blog. At Meural, we decided to implement server side rendering in order to increase our SEO exposure and to make social media sharing more effective. In this post, I’ll talk about how server side rendering works and the implementation that I developed. Background In traditional web applications, web pages are rendered on the client side. The browser receives a blob of JavaScript from the server, processes it, and paints the UI t...</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From Philosophy to Computer Science</title>
      <link>https://alexrichey.com/articles/from-philosophy-to-computer-science.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 May 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <description>When I say that I’m a software developer with a background in academic philosophy, many people react with surprise, as if I had jumped between completely divergent fields. Philosophy and computer science are in fact closely related and it is easy to transition from one to the other. In this article I would like to highlight a few reasons why this is so, with the hopes of dispelling the common misperception that they are opposites and of giving some background for students of philosophy who are interested...</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SkiFree</title>
      <link>https://alexrichey.com/articles/skifree.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <description>Here's a clone of the classic game SkiFree that I made with Javascript Canvas as part of a/A's curriculum. Check out the repo on GitHub here. Click to begin and use the mouse to control your skier. #canvas { display: block; border: 1px solid #ccc; border-radius: 6px; width: 500px; height: 500px; background-image: url('/assets/ski-free-background.png'); background-size: contain; } @media screen and (max-width: 500px) { #canvas { width: 100%; } }</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>