<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Alex Richey | Blog</title><link>https://alexrichey.com</link><language>en-us</language><description>Software engineer based in Seattle, WA. I write about politics and code.</description><pubDate>2021-01-27 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</pubDate><lastBuildDate>2021-01-27 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</lastBuildDate><item><title>Posterity</title><link>https://alexrichey.com/articles/2021-01-27-posterity.html</link><pubDate>2021-01-27 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</pubDate><description>I decided to shut down Convo last week, a project that I had labored on for more than a year. What led me to this decision was that I finally realized that Convo lacked cohesion among its features—it wasn't sure what it was trying to be and I wasn't sure anymore either.</description></item><item><title>On Looting</title><link>https://alexrichey.com/articles/2020-06-05-on-looting.html</link><pubDate>2020-06-05 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</pubDate><description>It is in one’s interest to follow the law when one is also protected by the law. But if one is not protected by the law, then what interest does one have in following it?</description></item><item><title>Docker Commands</title><link>https://alexrichey.com/articles/2019-10-30-docker-commands.html</link><pubDate>2019-10-30 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</pubDate><description>I use Docker all the time. But still I forget common commands constantly. Here are the commands I need to look up most often.</description></item><item><title>Bringing Meural's Frontend to the Bleeding Edge</title><link>https://alexrichey.com/articles/2018-07-10-bringing-our-frontend-to-the-bleeding-edge.html</link><pubDate>2018-07-10 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</pubDate><description>My article on my.meural's redesign originally published on Meural's Product Blog.</description></item><item><title>Setting Up Server Side Rendering with React, Redux, and Django</title><link>https://alexrichey.com/articles/2017-12-29-setting-up-ssr-react-django.html</link><pubDate>2017-12-29 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</pubDate><description>My article on server side rendering originally published on Meural's Product Blog.</description></item><item><title>From Philosophy to Computer Science</title><link>https://alexrichey.com/articles/2016-05-21-from-philosophy-to-cs.html</link><pubDate>2016-05-21 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</pubDate><description>When I say that I’m a software developer with a background in academic philosophy, many people react with surprise, as if I had jumped between completely divergent fields. Philosophy and computer science are in fact closely related and it is easy to transition from one to the other. In this article I would like to highlight a few reasons why this is so, with the hopes of dispelling the common misperception that they are opposites and of giving some background for students of philosophy who are interested in transitioning to computer science.</description></item><item><title>SkiFree</title><link>https://alexrichey.com/articles/2016-04-17-ski-free.html</link><pubDate>2016-04-17 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</pubDate><description>Here's a clone of the classic game SkiFree that I made with Javascript Canvas as part of a/A's curriculum. Check out the repo on GitHub here. Click to begin and use the mouse to control your skier.</description></item><item><title>Two Kinds of Racism</title><link>https://alexrichey.com/articles/2016-01-21-two-kinds-of-racism.html</link><pubDate>2016-01-21 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</pubDate><description>In George Yancy’s article “Dear White America,” he writes:</description></item><item><title>Ted Sider’s Solution to the Problem of Radical Semantic Skepticism</title><link>https://alexrichey.com/articles/2015-12-06-ted-siders-solution-to-the-problem-of-radical-semantic-skepticism.html</link><pubDate>2015-12-06 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</pubDate><description>Link to a paper I wrote on Columbia Academic Commons. Here's the abstract:</description></item><item><title>Against Pessimism</title><link>https://alexrichey.com/articles/2014-02-24-against-pessimism.html</link><pubDate>2014-02-24 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</pubDate><description>My article about pessimism originally published on 3QuarksDaily.</description></item><item><title>What the Science of Happiness Can Tell Us About Taxes</title><link>https://alexrichey.com/articles/2013-07-10-what-the-science-of-happiness-can-tell-us-about-taxes.html</link><pubDate>2013-07-10 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</pubDate><description>My article about the relationship between happiness and income, originally published on PolicyMic.</description></item><item><title>Minimum Wage Bill: Obama's $9 Proposal Won't Increase Unemployment</title><link>https://alexrichey.com/articles/2013-06-09-minimum-wage-bill-obamas-9-proposal-wont-increase-unemployment.html</link><pubDate>2013-06-09 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</pubDate><description>My article on minimum wage, originally published on PolicyMic.</description></item><item><title>The Lame Duck Dilemma</title><link>https://alexrichey.com/articles/2012-09-15-the-lame-duck-dilemma.html</link><pubDate>2012-09-15 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</pubDate><description>There has been no shortage of articles declaring that the lame duck congress is intransigent. Paul Krugman of the New York Times, for example, writes that the most striking feature of Obama’s presidency is not his management of the troubled economy, but “the scorched-earth opposition of Republicans.” Perhaps the most salient episode of Republican opposition occurred last summer, when Republicans threatened a government shut-down by posturing to deny raising the debt-ceiling and reduced the nation’s credit rating in the process.</description></item></channel></rss>