<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>Alex Richey | Blog</title><link>https://alexrichey.com</link><language>en-us</language><description>Software engineer based in Seattle, WA. I write about politics and code.</description><pubDate>2021-04-01 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</pubDate><lastBuildDate>2021-04-01 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</lastBuildDate><item><title>Notes on Ben Orenstein's "Refactoring from Good to Great"</title><link>https://alexrichey.com/articles/2021-04-01-orenstien-refactoring.html</link><pubDate>2021-04-01 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</pubDate><description>I watched Ben Orenstein's talk "Refactoring from Good to Great" at the beginning of my career and it made big and, I think, positive impact on how I write code. Here are some notes I took on the original talk to make its content easier to share.</description></item><item><title>Posterity</title><link>https://alexrichey.com/articles/2021-01-27-posterity.html</link><pubDate>2021-01-27 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</pubDate><description>I decided to shut down Convo last week, a project that I had labored on for more than a year. What led me to this decision was that I finally realized that Convo lacked cohesion among its features—it wasn't sure what it was trying to be and I wasn't sure anymore either.</description></item><item><title>On Looting</title><link>https://alexrichey.com/articles/2020-06-05-on-looting.html</link><pubDate>2020-06-05 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</pubDate><description>It is in one’s interest to follow the law when one is also protected by the law. But if one is not protected by the law, then what interest does one have in following it?</description></item><item><title>Docker Commands</title><link>https://alexrichey.com/articles/2019-10-30-docker-commands.html</link><pubDate>2019-10-30 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</pubDate><description>I use Docker all the time. But still I forget common commands constantly. Here are the commands I need to look up most often.</description></item><item><title>Bringing Meural's Frontend to the Bleeding Edge</title><link>https://alexrichey.com/articles/2018-07-10-bringing-our-frontend-to-the-bleeding-edge.html</link><pubDate>2018-07-10 00:00:00 +0000 UTC</pubDate><description>When we decided to redesign our flagship web app at Meural, we took the opportunity to rethink our approach to React and other frontend infrastructure. We ultimately decided to migrate from our own home-cooked server side rendering solution to Next.js, to change our approach to data handling with Redux, and to adopt styled-components. These decisions enabled us to develop and deploy our new frontend in just two months. In this article, I’ll talk about the upshot of these choices and about how things have worked out in production.</description></item></channel></rss>